Council on Foreign Relations Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989: Finding Aid MC104.13
Public Policy Papers
- Series 1: Digital Sound Recordings, 1953-1989; 24 boxes
  - The Far-Eastern Policy of the United States, 1953 December 30; Rockefeller III, John D.; Smith, H. Alexander (Howard Alexander), 1880-1966; 1 box (Box 729)
    H. (Howard) Alexander Smith served as the executive secretary of Princeton University and was later elected to the United States Senate representing New Jersey. Smith made contributions to United States foreign policy while serving on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
    H. Alexander Smith was born in New York City on January 30, 1880. His father, Abram Alexander Smith, was a respected physician and teacher. Smith attended high school at the Cutler School, a private prep school. He studied as an undergraduate at Princeton, graduating with an A.B. in 1901. While at Princeton, he befriended Professor Woodrow Wilson. Wilson penned a letter of recommendation for Smith, which helped him get accepted to Columbia Law School.
    During his time at Columbia, Smith met Helen Dominick, daughter of a prominent New York City lawyer. They married in 1902 and had their first child, Helen, in 1903. Smith graduated from Columbia Law in 1904 and passed the New York State Bar exam shortly there after. After graduation, Smith began his career working for the Legal Aid Society in New York City. However, Smith developed tuberculosis shortly after and relocated to the cleaner and drier air of Colorado in an attempt to ease the complications associated with his illness. Smith passed the Colorado Bar exam in 1906 and slowly returned to legal practice. He spent his first few years in Colorado between legal work for the law firm of Lunt, Brooks and Wilcox and a land investment venture with a partner at the firm. After the investment failed in 1911, Smith partnered with Daniel Knowlton to establish the firm of Smith and Knowlton. The firm focused on cases involving public utilities, natural resources, estates, and property.
    Though Smith was a relatively successful attorney, he maintained a desire to serve the public. He jumped at an opportunity to turn to public service at the outbreak of World War I. Smith involved himself in relief work, helping to raise money for various charities that aimed to provide relief to war-torn European nations. In order to focus what he considered at scattershot relief effort, Smith organized the War Sufferers' Relief Committee in 1916.
    Smith became directly involved in government service after the United States' entry into World War I. Unable to pass the Army physical, he took the position Federal Food Administrator for El Paso County. Smith worked to enroll families in the food conservation program to aid the war effort. The county office was a division of the United States Food Administration, and after distinguishing himself through this work, Herbert Hoover tapped Smith to join the staff of the Food Administration in Washington, D.C. Smith arrived in Washington in December 1917 and began working in the cooperating organizations section of the States Administration Division of the Food Administration. The responsibility of his position involved streamlining operations, and identifying needs and targeting the best religious, fraternal, or social organization that could fulfill those needs.
    While in Washington, Smith developed a renewed interest in his alma mater. Smith was encouraged by fellow alumni critical of current university policy to visit Princeton, and after receiving approval from President John Grier Hibben, he spent two months of 1919 interviewing administration, faculty, and trustees. Shortly after completing this task, Hibben offered Smith a position at the University. Smith spent the next year chairing the Committee on University Organization, which surveyed finances, academics, campus life, the endowment campaign, and the University's future goals, and concluded that the University needed to operate in a more business-like, streamlined manner. Among the committee's recommendations were plans to overhaul alumni activities, expand fundraising, raise faculty salaries, and reorganize administrative offices and operations. Included in the committee's suggestions for administrative reorganization was the proposal to create the position of executive secretary, a role intended to serve as an assistant to the president. Smith became the first person to hold the position in the fall of 1920, and he spent the next several years attempting to implement many of the committee's recommendations.
    Smith's relationship with Princeton became strained after he differed with administration's handling of the Philadelphian Society, a campus religious group that fell under the influence of the controversial Frank N. D. Buchman. The basic tenants of Buchmanism preached living a life free of sin while setting aside time each day for quiet reflection in which one searched for divine guidance. However, the Buchmanites tended to be aggressive in their tactics when they evangelized to those they considered sinners. After Buchmanism caused a small national stir in the mid-1920s, President Hibben ordered an investigation of the Philadelphian Society on campus. Hibben concluded that the Philadelphian Society was distracting students from their studies and recommended that the Society's campus activities be scaled back. Smith disagreed, was sympathetic toward Buchman, and felt that President Hibben did not take Buchman's criticism of the University seriously enough. Smith converted to Buchmanism shortly after the controversy. He was a deeply religious person and remained in correspondence with Buchman and other followers of the movement throughout his life.
    Smith ultimately resigned from his executive secretary position as a result from his dispute with President Hibben but remained at Princeton. In the fall of 1928, he began a new position as a lecturer in the department of politics. Smith's courses focused on international relations and United States foreign policy. However, Smith quickly became disillusioned with the secular direction of Princeton and teaching and left the university in 1930.
    After resigning from his position at Princeton, Smith continued to live in town as he began practicing law in New York City. Though Smith worked part-time for the firm of Dominick and Dominick, he spent much of the next decade focusing on the New Jersey Republican Party. In 1933, Smith helped form the New Jersey Republican Policy Council, which aimed to organize many of the small, local Republican clubs to promote the party within the state. The council lasted only a year, forced to disband due to lack of interest and funding. Though the Policy Council had failed, Smith did succeed in making a name for himself within the New Jersey Republican Party. In 1934, Smith was offered the position of treasurer of the New Jersey Republican State Committee, which functioned as the chief fund raiser for the state party.
    During Smith's tenure as treasurer, the state party underwent a bitter split. Smith's reputation as a bipartisan mediator helped him get elected as chairman of the Republican State Committee. Smith was seen as a safe, non-offensive pick that could help reunite the state party. Though Smith was only moderately successful in mending the split in the party, he had positioned himself for to run for elected office. The death of Senator H. Warren Barbour in November of 1943 left one of New Jersey's seats vacant. Smith politicked hard and sought to win broad party support. His bridge-building and hard work paid off – in 1944 he was elected to the United States Senate to serve the remaining two years of Barbour's term.
    As a freshman senator, Smith was assigned to the committees of Education and Labor, District of Columbia, Judiciary, Privileges and Elections, and Public Buildings and Grounds. He was transferred from the Judiciary Committee to the Military Affairs Committee in 1945. Though much of Smith's time as a freshman senator was spent in becoming acclimated to his new position, he did involve himself in the debate over the Reciprocal Trade Act. Smith broke with the majority of the Republican Party and supported the Reciprocal Trade Act and lower tariffs.
    Smith won re-election in 1946 and spent much of 1946 and early 1947 focusing on labor/management relations. Smith often sided with management on issues of strike and wages and ultimately supported the renewal of the Taft-Hartley Act. After re-election, Smith left all committees but the Education and Labor and was chosen to fill one of the three vacant Republican seats on the Foreign Relations Committee. An appointment on the Foreign Relations Committee was a career milestone for Smith, as foreign policy was Smith's primary interest. As a result, Smith devoted most of his time to the committee.
    Always a staunch anti-Communist, Smith was a strong supporter of the Voice of America radio station, which was established during World War II to broadcast programming favorable to American policy across Europe. Late in 1947, Smith toured Europe in order to build a case for Voice of America. When he returned to the U.S., he wrote a report that helped win support for the Smith-Mundt Bill, passed in 1948, which reorganized and provided funding for Voice of America.
    Throughout 1948 and 1949, Smith continued his fight against Communism, turning his attention to Far East Asia and the Chinese Civil War. In September of 1948, Smith visited Japan, Hong Kong, and the Philippines with the goal of determining the ability of Nationalist leader Chiang Kai-shek. The trip convinced Smith that a Communist China and Taiwan would offer a global threat. When he returned, he urged the Congress to support the Nationalists. Smith had positioned himself as a follower of the policy of containment and remained committed to idea that the U.S. and U.N. should not recognize Communist China. After the Communists sized control of China and Taiwan, Smith turned his attention to Korea. He strongly supported the Korean War and disagreed with President Truman's dismissal of General MacArthur. In 1953, Smith toured Korea and Indo-China which resulted in Smith turning his attention to the conflict which would ultimately become the Vietnam War. Again, Smith believed strongly the U.S. involvement in Southeast Asia could prevent additional countries from falling into the Communist sphere.
    Stateside, Smith spent 1951 and 1952 campaigning for re-election. He backed Dwight Eisenhower for president and won re-election to the Senate in 1952. His third term saw a continued interest in Taft-Hartley and labor/management relations. Smith also focused on transportation projects and amnesty cases for his New Jersey constituency. In 1954, Smith voted to censure Senate Joseph McCarthy. Though he generally supported McCarthy's goals, he disagreed strongly with his approach.
    In late-1957, Smith's wife fell ill which prompted Smith to withdraw his name for re-election in 1958. He officially left the Senate on January 3, 1959. Shortly after leaving the Senate, John Foster Dulles offered Smith the position of Special Consultant on Foreign Affairs to the Secretary of State. With his wife in better health, Smith accepted the position wanting to remain active in U.S. foreign policy matters. Smith's job was to offer his opinion and recommendations directly to Dulles. A significant moment during Smith's tenure as special consultant came when he undertook a friendly, diplomatic trip across Asia and reported his findings to Dulles.
    Smith officially retired to his home in Princeton in 1960. He remained in constant contact with former colleagues in New Jersey and Washington, often offering opinions and advice. He also continued his interest in Princeton University and his Class of 1901. He died on October 27th, 1966.
  - Postwar International Relations: A Third Phase?, 1954 February 16; Makins, Sir Roger; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-16A
  - Problems of Weapons Development in the Cold War, 1954 March 4; Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991; Crawford, Kenneth; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-16B
  - The Soviet Union in 1954: An Eyewitness View, 1954 February 18; Macduffie, Marshall 1909-1967; Robinson, Geroid T.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-17A
  - How to Control the German Army, 1954 February 23; Detloff, Gerhard, Graf von Schwerin, 1899-1980; Shuster, George N.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-17B
  - Britain's Role in NATO, 1954 March 11; Finletter, Thomas K. (Thomas Knight), 1893-1980; Simpson, Frank; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-18A
  - United States' Defense Policy: The New Look (United States Defense Policy 1), 1954 March 15; Spofford, Charles M.; Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-18B
  - Implications of the Berlin Conference, 1954 March 17; Bowie, Robert R., (Robert Richardson) 1909-2013; Josephs, Devereux C.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-19A
  - Defense Against the New Weapons" (United States Defense Policy 3), 1954 March 29; Kelly, Mervin J.; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-19B
  - Japan and Her Neighbors, 1954 April 5; Dean, Arthur H.; Rockefeller, John D.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-20A
  - The Views of the Social Democratic Party on Germany's Relations with the Western Allies, 1954 April 7; Schmid, Carlo; Stone, Shepard; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-20B
    Speech in German.
  - Foreign Investment in the Netherlands, 1954 April 12; Kramer, E. L.; Rockefeller, David, 1915-2017; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-21A
  - Implications of the Caracas Conference, 1954 April 21; Holland, Henry F.; Johnson, Joseph E. (Joseph Esrey), 1906-1990; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-21B
  - Current Conditions in Western German, 1954 April 29; Conant, James B.; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-22A
  - European Attitudes toward United States' Foreign Policy, 1954 May 6; Burden, William A. M. (William Armistead Moale), 1906-1984; Goormaghtigh, J. (John); 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-22B
  - Postwar Evolution of Soviet Policy, 1954 May 11; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005; Tucker, Robert C.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-23A
    George F. Kennan (1904-2005) was a diplomat and a historian, noted especially for his influence on United States policy towards the Soviet Union during the Cold War and for his scholarly expertise in the areas of Russian history and foreign policy. While with the Foreign Service, Kennan advocated a policy of "containment" that influenced United States relations with the Soviet Union throughout the Cold War and served in various positions in European embassies, as well as ambassador to the Soviet Union. His career as a historian was spent at the Institute for Advanced Study, where he continued to analyze the history of Russia, Soviet Union and United States foreign policies, and foreign affairs.
    Kennan was educated at St. John's Northwestern Military Academy in Delafield, Wisconsin and earned his B.A. degree at Princeton University in 1925, where he studied history with an emphasis on modern European diplomacy. Following graduation, he entered the Foreign Service. His first post was as vice consul in Geneva, and in the next year he was transferred to Hamburg, Germany. In 1928, Kennan entered a training program though the Foreign Service, studying Russian language, history and culture at Berlin University. The United States did not yet have diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union, and so Kennan was assigned to "listening posts" around the U.S.S.R. in Tallinn, Estonia (1927) and in Riga, Latvia and Kaunas, Lithuania (1931-1933).
    His first assignment in Moscow came in 1933 under William C. Bullitt, the first United States ambassador to the Soviet Union, aiding in the establishment of diplomatic relations between Washington and the Kremlin for the first time since 1917. He held positions as third secretary from 1933 to 1934, second secretary from 1935 to 1936, and from 1944 to 1946, minister-counselor (the second highest rank at the embassy), first under W. Averell Harriman and then under General Walter Bedell Smith. During this period, he was also appointed to positions in Vienna (1935), Prague (1938), Berlin (1939), Lisbon (1942), and London (1944). Kennan was detained in Berlin for five months after United States' entry into World War II.
    Kennan rose to prominence in February 1946 when he wrote what became known as the "Long Telegram." Written in response to an inquiry from the U.S. Treasury regarding Moscow's refusal to support the World Bank and International Monetary Fund, the telegram outlined Kennan's assessment of the psychology of the leaders of the Soviet Union and provided principles on which the United States should base policies towards the Soviet Union. Kennan wrote that Stalin was "impervious to the logic of reason but highly sensitive to the logic of force," by which he meant primarily diplomatic and economic force more so than military. The telegram resonated in Washington, D.C.--although the interpretation of the Soviet threat became predominantly described as a military one--and Kennan became an influential figure in the State Department on Soviet affairs. Kennan further developed his views in "The Sources of Soviet Conduct" published under the pseudonym X in Foreign Affairs in July 1947. In this article, he used the term "containment" to describe his philosophy for dealing with the spread of Soviet power and influence. Again, this was interpreted by others in Washington as a military strategy, although Kennan intended it to be primarily achieved through diplomacy, economic sanctions, and covert action--anything short of war. Containment became one of the primary rationales for United States' Cold War policies, including the Marshall Plan, the founding of NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization) in 1949, the commitment of American forces in Southeast Asia in 1965, and the Reagan administration arms buildup during the 1980s.
    In April 1946, Kennan returned to Washington, D.C., where he taught at the National War College, and in 1947, he was appointed director of the Policy Planning Staff in the State Department. In this capacity, he was a principle architect of the Marshall Plan, which sent billions of dollars of aid to help rebuild Western Europe following World War II. When Dean Acheson became Secretary of State in 1949, Kennan remained in the State Department as one of his principal advisors. However, during this period Kennan became increasingly critical of United States policy, especially the military interpretation of containment and the entry of UN troops into North Korea, and so in 1950 Kennan took a leave of absence to devote himself to research and scholarship at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, New Jersey.
    Kennan returned to the State Department in March 1952 when President Harry S. Truman appointed him Ambassador to the U.S.S.R. The assignment was short-lived, however. Kept under heavy surveillance by the Soviets, in October 1952 he compared conditions to those he suffered under his Nazi internment during World War II, and the Soviet government declared him persona non grata, which forced his return to the United States. Because of policy differences between Kennan and Secretary of State John Foster Dulles (who found containment too passive), Dulles employed a technicality to force Kennan's retirement from the State Department in 1953.
    He returned to the Institute for Advanced Study, where he became a professor in the School of Historical Studies in 1956. Kennan became a prolific and respected diplomatic historian, studying modern European and Russian history, international relations, and American foreign policy and diplomacy. He also remained an important, often critical, voice in the ongoing debate about American foreign policy, advocating the use of diplomacy rather than military force and for foreign policy that was "very modest and restrained." Kennan was critical of the buildup of conventional and nuclear weapons during the arms race, which many argued for in the name of containment. He also advocated against military involvement in Vietnam, indicating that it was not an area of the world critical to American security. Later in his career, Kennan became a supporter of Russian and Soviet studies in the United States, identifying scholarship as a productive means to establish favorable relations with Moscow.
    Over the course of his career, Kennan wrote numerous influential and critically acclaimed books, including American Diplomacy 1900-1950 (1951), Russia Leaves the War (1956), Russia and the West Under Lenin and Stalin (1961), two volumes of memoirs (1967, 1972), The Decline of Bismarck's European Order (1979), The Nuclear Delusion (1982), and Around the Cragged Hill (1993). He won two Pulitzer Prizes, one for Russia Leaves the War and the other for the first volume of his memoirs. Though he remained at the Institute for Advanced Study until his retirement in 1974, Kennan did return to government service briefly on two occasions, as ambassador to Yugoslavia from 1961 until 1963 for President John F. Kennedy and traveling to Switzerland in 1967 as a representative for the State Department to help convince Svetlana Alliluyeva, the daughter of Josef Stalin, to immigrate to the United States.
    George Frost Kennan was born on February 16, 1904 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin to Kossuth Kent Kennan, a lawyer, and Florence (James) Kennan. He met Annelise Sorensen of Norway while studying in Berlin and they married in 1931. The Kennans had four children: Grace Kennan Warnecke, Joan Kennan, Wendy Kennan, and Christopher J. Kennan. Through the course of his career, Kennan was the recipient of many honors for his work in the field of international affairs, including the Albert Einstein Peace Prize (1981), the Peace Prize of the German Book Trade (1982), the Gold Medal in History of the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters (1984), the FDR Freedom from Fear Award (1987), and the Presidential Medal of Freedom (1989, the highest civilian honor in the United States). George Kennan died on March 17, 2005 in Princeton, New Jersey at the age of 101.
  - Political Stability in France: Problems of Constitutional Revision, 1954 May 13; Goguel, Francois; Rodgers, Lindsey; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-23B
  - United States Inter-American Policy, 1954 May 17; Lleras Camargo, Alberto, 1906-1990.; Miller, Edward G., Jr; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-24A
  - Joint Development of the Jordan River Valley, 1955 April 13; Gross, Ernest A.; Johnston, Eric; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-24B
  - United States Inter-American Policy, 1954 May 17; Lleras Camargo, Alberto, 1906-1990.; Miller, Edward G., Jr; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-25A
  - Suez in the Light of Recent International Developments, 1954 May 17; Georges-Picot, Jacques; Spofford, Charles M.; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-25B
  - Burmese Developments Since Independence, 1954 May 24; Barrington, James; Jessup, Philip C. (Philip Caryl), 1897-1986; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-26A
  - Untitled, 1954 June 2; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Haile Selassie I; 1 box (Box 729)
    MC104-26B
  - A Report on the Geneva Conference, 1954 July 1; McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989; Smith, Walter Bedell, 1895-1961; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-27A
  - Problems of Economic Development in India, 1954 September 14; Birla, G. D.; Dean, Arthur H.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-27B
  - Germany's Future Policies in Europe, 1954 September 22; Krekeler, Heinz L.; Shuster, George N.; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-28A
  - China as Seen from Hong Kong, 1954 September 29; Grantham, Alexander, 1899-1978; Johnson, Joseph E. (Joseph Esrey), 1906-1990; 1 box (Box 730)
    MC104-28B